[SPEAKER_00]: In his bowling alley in Bentley, it's the Bowick Incorporated.
[SPEAKER_00]: We finished up the other side of the tape in March with Mickey Vernon and Mr. Gorska pitched against him.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wonder if you could just start in talking about Mickey Vernon here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you remember much about him?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, very vaguely because it's been so many years that
[SPEAKER_01]: It's hard to remember way back when, when you've been inactive.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only contact I have with the sport anymore is through the sporting news or the sport pages.
[SPEAKER_01]: Our local paper doesn't carry too much news, as you notice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when I have time, I do read the sporting news.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if they appear in the paper somewhere, I scan it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tell me, how did you get located here in Beckley?
[SPEAKER_01]: When I signed my first baseball contract, it was with Charleston Senators of the Middle Atlantic League back in 1937.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I came down here that spring with high hopes of being the first baseman for the Senators.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when I got here, the manager was playing first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who was the manager?
[SPEAKER_01]: Iggy Walters, 330 hitter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Iggy?
[SPEAKER_01]: Iggy Walters.
[SPEAKER_01]: He managed the ball club and played first in the Tiger team then.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you see what chance I had to play first base.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: This was a Tiger property then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was a Class C league.
[SPEAKER_01]: Madden Middle Atlantic, which was, in those days, a very fast league.
[SPEAKER_00]: Who were the teams in that league at that time?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, they had Johnstown, Youngstown, Zanesville, Ohio, Youngstown, Ohio.
[SPEAKER_01]: in Akron, Ohio, which was a Yankee farm.
[SPEAKER_00]: How'd you travel around in that league?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I didn't get to start the season in that league.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before the season started, I was shipped to Beckley.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were cutting the squad.
[SPEAKER_01]: They had no room for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I came to Beckley and played first base for the Beckley Bengals in 37.
[SPEAKER_01]: That'd be the Mountain State League.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was the Mountain State League in those days.
[SPEAKER_01]: And before the season was over, they were trying to convert me to a pitcher.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I held my ground until the season was over.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the following year, I went down to Beaumont for spring training and came back here to pitch in 1938.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I spent the season here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why did they convert you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Did you just have a good arm, came, showed up?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I looked up in Detroit.
[SPEAKER_01]: They had Greenberg and Rudy Young playing first base.
[SPEAKER_01]: They didn't need a first baseman for many years.
[SPEAKER_01]: So they thought they'd better
[SPEAKER_01]: try to strengthen elsewhere so I could throw the ball hard and I thought I'd make a better pitcher.
[SPEAKER_00]: How did you hit with it back there in 37?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well in 37 I hit 299, about 14 or 15 home runs.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where was the ballpark here in those days?
[SPEAKER_00]: The ballpark
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still around to be where the Raleigh Motor Sales Pontiac garage is now down here in Raleigh Heights On the south side of town about a mile and a half from here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it much of a ballpark?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it was a little classy ballpark sandy infield and outfield Not much to play on but it was a ballpark draw very well well Sad to say that we couldn't go up to well even with a winning ballclub but
[SPEAKER_01]: I think we attribute that to the climate here.
[SPEAKER_01]: It gets pretty cold at night.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was mostly night baseball and couldn't get too many people to sit out in that weather.
[SPEAKER_01]: How were the lights?
[SPEAKER_01]: The lights were fair.
[SPEAKER_01]: We got by.
[SPEAKER_02]: So your wife was from here?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, she lived here.
[SPEAKER_01]: is a pharmacist at the White Cross Pharmacy uptown, and she's still there for that matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I know.
[SPEAKER_02]: We tried to see her yesterday.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, we got her name.
[SPEAKER_01]: We want to see her for the repairs.
[SPEAKER_01]: And of course, I met her in 37, the summer of 37.
[SPEAKER_01]: We were married in the fall of 38, at the end of that 38th season.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, after that season was over, I was sent to Beaumont, Texas, in the Texas League.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was there one year.
[SPEAKER_01]: 38 in Beaumont.
[SPEAKER_01]: How was your?
[SPEAKER_01]: 39.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then in spring of 40, I went to Detroit and stayed there until 1947.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you made your home here from that time?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: My home is here from the time we were married until.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, that's nice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nice.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've been living here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I like it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a great state.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a great town.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the climate here is beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's a peaceful life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Who signed you to a contract originally?
[SPEAKER_01]: I was playing ball on the Sandlots, semi-pro ball up in New Jersey at the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: In those days, they had a lot of bird dog scouts.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were not regular scouts on the staff, but they would help us.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know what I'm talking about when I say bird dog.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've heard the term, but I... A bird dog scout is one who works for a scout.
[SPEAKER_01]: Scout can't cover all the territory.
[SPEAKER_01]: In those days they didn't have too many.
[SPEAKER_01]: So he would have spotters in different sections.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this fellow was one up in New Jersey.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he came to watch somebody else.
[SPEAKER_01]: In this particular game I was playing in the Union County League.
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess I must have had a pretty good day and impressed him, so he offered me a contract and I signed it.
[SPEAKER_01]: How were you playing that day?
[SPEAKER_01]: I was playing third base that day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Quite all over.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then that would have been in 36 that he signed you?
[SPEAKER_00]: That was in 36.
[SPEAKER_01]: He signed me up for the next spring, and that's when I went to Charleston.
[SPEAKER_01]: But before I was through there, the head scout, Jack Zeller, from Detroit came down.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was fooling around the outfield that particular day, and he saw how I could throw.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the first thing he said, you ought to be a pitcher.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then I think he put Watt Powell up to it, who managed the Barclayville and won the Barclayville at that time.
[SPEAKER_01]: He gave him all those minutes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Watt worked on me, but I wouldn't listen.
[SPEAKER_01]: I said, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: I came to play first.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't play first out.
[SPEAKER_00]: What was Watt Powell like?
[SPEAKER_01]: Watt Powell, well, we didn't see too much of him.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was the owner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like any owner, he was in the stands, but we didn't get to see or talk to him too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where did you play?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where's the ballpark in Charleston?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where it is right now?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on the same side as the Watt Powell Park?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same park.
[SPEAKER_01]: What did they call it?
[SPEAKER_01]: They call it...
[SPEAKER_01]: Senator Field or something?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, let's see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before they renamed it Watt Powell Park, it was...
[SPEAKER_01]: I forget what it was.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it is the same park.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same park.
[SPEAKER_00]: They didn't really rebuild a new park there.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, they just improved the old one.
[SPEAKER_00]: We've been a lot of games.
[SPEAKER_00]: In fact, we're going up there tonight to see the Charlies.
[SPEAKER_00]: OK, 1940, that was a great year, wasn't it, for the Tigers?
[SPEAKER_01]: That was a great year for the Tigers and for Johnny Gorsuch.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was the first year in my first year in the big leagues, and the first World Series I ever played in, and the last one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Did you pitch in the World Series?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, I pitched in two games.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, I was a relief pitcher.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being a single ball pitcher, they decided to make a relief pitcher out of me, so that's what I was doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, every now and then, they would spot pitch me against certain ball clubs, and I would start a game occasionally.
[SPEAKER_01]: I got in two ball games in the World Series.
[SPEAKER_01]: Both games I relieved schoolboy road starting pitch against Bucky Walters in Cincinnati Rays.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, they won both games and beat us both games, but.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the first game, I relieved him.
[SPEAKER_01]: I went in with a couple of men on base and one out.
[SPEAKER_01]: He already had a couple of runs across and.
[SPEAKER_01]: I threw a double play page and get out of the inning and.
[SPEAKER_01]: They didn't get a hit from me until
[SPEAKER_01]: Last inning I pitched, which was about the 8th, I believe.
[SPEAKER_01]: I pitched 5 in 2010, England's 10th inning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Retired the first 14 men in order, and the 15th man got scratch-hit to third base.
[SPEAKER_01]: Third baseman, slow coming in, and Spud Davis beat it out to first base.
[SPEAKER_01]: Slowly balling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so it was.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, anyway, that was the only hit they got out of me.
[SPEAKER_01]: But we lost the game, I think, 3 to 1, 3 to 2.
[SPEAKER_01]: Another real good performance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then I got to pitch again against Bucky again, won the schoolboy role, started the sixth game of the World Series.
[SPEAKER_01]: In that game, I pitched, I think it was 5 and 2 thirds innings and allowed about three hits, I believe, something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we lost that one, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then they went to the seventh game, and they beat us in the seventh.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's over 10 innings of that line of running.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had 11 and 1 third innings, I believe, with just one run scored against me.
[SPEAKER_01]: We scored one run in the second game.
[SPEAKER_00]: I grew up in Cleveland, was a great Cleveland Indian fan all these years.
[SPEAKER_00]: And of course, Cleveland almost won the pennant that year, but didn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the big game was the Giebel game.
[SPEAKER_00]: How was that choice made again?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I think the story that I got from some of the older heads, Hank Greenberg for one, we were talking about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we went into Cleveland two games in front.
[SPEAKER_01]: you remember and we went in on Friday and we knew Bob Fellow was going to pitch against us so we were going to concede that ballgame to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well they were trying to decide who to start against Cleveland and the choice was between Floyd Giebel and myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: See they had just brought Giebel up from Buffalo to end the season.
[SPEAKER_01]: So
[SPEAKER_01]: The powers that be decided, well, Giebel had more experience than I.
[SPEAKER_01]: He'd been pitching, and he was much older than I.
[SPEAKER_01]: He'd been pitching for a number of years, so they said, well, we'll go with Giebel because of his experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't know he had that much of an experience behind him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, yeah, he was...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's been mostly minorly, though.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, let's see, this was my second year pitching, third year pitching.
[SPEAKER_01]: So they started him, and as luck would have it, we beat Feller.
[SPEAKER_01]: I believe it was two to one.
[SPEAKER_01]: in that game and since the pen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the next day.
[SPEAKER_01]: They threw the ball and he said you're it today.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I started the next game on Saturday and I went seven and two thirds innings and allowed one hit and they brought Newsome in.
[SPEAKER_01]: I pitched seven innings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Newsome pitch the last two and when I left again we were leading one and nothing and I had one scratch hit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Roy Weatherly had a ground ball between.
[SPEAKER_01]: Second baseman in the bag and.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course,
[SPEAKER_01]: pulled me, said, well, we'll arrest him.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're going to be using him in the World Series.
[SPEAKER_01]: So Newsom went in, and of course, they finally beat us 2 to 1.
[SPEAKER_01]: He allowed two runs.
[SPEAKER_01]: We lost a game.
[SPEAKER_00]: You had the pennant won, though.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could you really bear down on those games?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, my goodness, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've got to bear down and get your brains beat out.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a matter of self-preservation, surely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Boy, I wasn't happy after that Eagle game.
[SPEAKER_01]: All us Cleveland fans, we were just
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's just the way it was.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, Cleveland, I think, was all tightened up and happy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Couldn't hit with the other hand.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was a year of the crybabies and everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oscar Viet and the ball players, I guess, fell out.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think I said, were you with them when they, in Cleveland, they dumped the fruit on Bertie Tebbets?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was at that game, I think, or right in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I was sitting right alongside of Tebbets when he got hit with that basket of fruit from the upper deck.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it knocked him out, really, because that basket, he was sitting on a bench, you know where the bullpen was in the stadium, down the left field line, and he was sitting on that low bench and that basket of fruit hit him right across the head and the shoulders.
[SPEAKER_01]: He just fell flat on his face.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were at least in the bullpen then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That basket of fruit came from the second deck.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of course, look what they throw now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Basket of fruit is quaint.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was at that game in Cleveland a couple weeks ago.
[SPEAKER_00]: riot and all the cherry bomb and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things have changed, huh?
[SPEAKER_00]: I'd say they have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, your best year was, which would you say here?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, 41, 9-11.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I had 7-7 the first year, 9-11 the second year.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then after that, you remember, I held out in 41, 42.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, tell me about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I held out for a little race and didn't get it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you negotiate with Jack Zeller?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I was negotiating with Jack Zeller.
[SPEAKER_00]: When did you report?
[SPEAKER_00]: Late?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh yes, I reported April 1st, but in the meantime I was conditioning here.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I got that spring training about April 1st, I was in good shape to pitch.
[SPEAKER_01]: You didn't really miss much?
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't miss much, but I was always a bug on conditioning.
[SPEAKER_01]: You look in great shape now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's go out there and pitch today.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Somebody fooled me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Probably the bowling helps keep you in shape.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I bowl, but I watch myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: What was your playing weight compared to now?
[SPEAKER_01]: My playing weight when I had to hang up the spikes was about 185.
[SPEAKER_01]: I weigh 200 right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: But most people probably wouldn't see the difference because in a uniform you look a little bigger.
[SPEAKER_01]: The uniforms we wore in those days were loose.
[SPEAKER_01]: Today they use them skin tight.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just don't know how they can do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you think that might constrict their movement some?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, to me it felt like it bound me if I had it tight on.
[SPEAKER_01]: We liked them loose.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were cooler.
[SPEAKER_00]: What did Zeller say when you
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, let me just say, I hadn't proved myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had to spend another year, have another winning season.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm like, I was just bad salesman, that's all.
[SPEAKER_00]: How was Del Baker, co-manager then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Del Baker was a good manager.
[SPEAKER_01]: Del was a good manager.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was good to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I thought Del was a good manager.
[SPEAKER_01]: because he'd been a coach with Detroit for many years before he was a manager before I even arrived.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no, I had no squabbles with management.
[SPEAKER_01]: I never had a problem with a manager.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only problem I had was with Zeller that one year, and that was it.
[SPEAKER_00]: How was the spirit on the Detroit team, say, in 40?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it was great.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was great.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could see the air about the boys.
[SPEAKER_01]: They had confidence that they were going to win a pennant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you remember back in that year, we went into the last month of the season, Labor Day, and we were three and a half games out of first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think we won about 17 out of 20 that year, that month, and went into first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Who was the big winning pitcher, Bridges?
[SPEAKER_01]: Buck Newsom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, Buck, I think, won 21 of 22 games.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Bridges won about 15.
[SPEAKER_01]: Schoolboy Rowe won about 16 that year.
[SPEAKER_01]: That could come back.
[SPEAKER_01]: And of course, we had Al Neuhauser.
[SPEAKER_01]: He won 9 and 9.
[SPEAKER_01]: I won 7 and 7.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dizzy Trout had a bad year.
[SPEAKER_01]: He only won three games that year.
[SPEAKER_01]: But his problem was his weight.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was mid-season before he could even get in shape.
[SPEAKER_01]: He'd taken a job selling beer the winter before, and...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think he thought he had the drink of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess after retirement, he really ballooned, too, didn't he?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, evidently so, but, uh... Three hundred pounds, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That trout?
[SPEAKER_01]: Did he get off that beer?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, Paul Frizz, a friend of mine in Terre Haute, where the trout was from.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knew him, and I think I told you something.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't believe it, because I hadn't seen Diz for many years, and only recently.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I think he died about a year or two ago, and he was living in Chicago.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think he was a sportscaster.
[SPEAKER_00]: That may be high, but he put on some weight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bobo Newsom, was he the great jollifier that he was painted?
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's put it this way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bobo liked his good times.
[SPEAKER_01]: Off the field, on the field.
[SPEAKER_00]: Was he a good influence?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, anybody that wins ball games on that ball field will be a good influence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, other than that, I never saw him off the field.
[SPEAKER_01]: I never associated with him.
[SPEAKER_01]: All I know is what I heard, and that's immaterial.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the way a man moves around like that, there must have been some grounds for his opinion, so I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Was it Newsom's father who died just before he pitched that claim?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, his father died.
[SPEAKER_01]: I saw his father the night before in the elevator.
[SPEAKER_01]: We went up the elevator together at the old Netherland Plaza, which is now, what is it, Netherland Hilton.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he died that night in Duck Pits, I think, the next day.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he won, didn't he?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he won.
[SPEAKER_00]: That must have been an emotional moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that was something.
[SPEAKER_01]: But those things happen, I guess.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wonder how the Cincinnati players played that game.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were kind of hard to beat, too, I expect.
[SPEAKER_01]: Probably, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no psychology to pitch Newsom because of that, anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well...
[SPEAKER_01]: He wasn't one to start, and he was the right one, so we went along with him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you know Tommy Bridges very well?
[SPEAKER_01]: Tommy was... Tommy was a good fellow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tommy was a good pitcher.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very quiet.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tommy didn't associate too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he was very capable.
[SPEAKER_01]: He worked his one game a week because of his age.
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess Tommy was 35.
[SPEAKER_01]: He pitched one a week.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he always gave a good performance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tommy was a real competitor.
[SPEAKER_00]: What was your outfield in 40?
[SPEAKER_01]: In 40, we had Barney McCoskey in center field.
[SPEAKER_01]: We had Greenberg playing left field.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rudy York was on first.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the year they moved Greenberg to left field, to make room for York.
[SPEAKER_01]: You remember, about a year or two before that, they tried York at catching.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he played third too, a little bit?
[SPEAKER_00]: York?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I don't think so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not while I was there, anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I guess he just could move around back there, satisfy the management, so then put him back on first and move Greenberg to left.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep those big sticks in the lineup.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in right field, we had Pete Fox and Bruce Campbell.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bruce Campbell was left-handed hitter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pete Fox was a right-handed hitter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then on the bench, we had Earl Averill as a pinch hitter and utility outfielder.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Tabitz was the catcher, Bertie Tabitz.
[SPEAKER_01]: On third base, we had Pinky Higgins, and that's the year Bartell played short for us.
[SPEAKER_01]: They got him from the Giants the year before.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've seen an owner stick there.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, Marvin was with Boston, I think, in 39.
[SPEAKER_01]: They got Higgins in 39.
[SPEAKER_01]: Garinger was playing second.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, he was still there, wasn't he?
[SPEAKER_00]: He was a mechanical man.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Billy Sullivan was the utility player.
[SPEAKER_00]: He caught and filled in the outfield, too.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pretty good hitter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Did these older players give you encouragement in your first year?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Surely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, they were always willing to help.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's one thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you're on the same team when you're out for one purpose, to win.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only way you can win is to play together.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if they could see where they can help you, they were always willing to offer encouragement and advice.
[SPEAKER_00]: What about 45?
[SPEAKER_00]: Were you in service that year?
[SPEAKER_00]: I went in service in spring of 45.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you think that had any effect on your career?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I don't think so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you pitch in service?
[SPEAKER_01]: I pitched with Great Lakes with Bob Fellow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, we had Pinky Higgins in service at the time, too, and Walkie Cooper.
[SPEAKER_00]: You must have won some titles up there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I think we lost one game this summer.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's quite a team.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, of course, we played exhibition games on the station up there.
[SPEAKER_01]: We played some major league ball clubs.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Fella was doing all the pitching on the main station.
[SPEAKER_01]: And of course, when we got off the station and played away from it, why then we wouldn't be doing the pitching.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I was playing in field and outfield.
[SPEAKER_01]: I found a lakes team because Fowler did all the pitching at home and we were short of ballplayers.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'd play first base, I'd play shortstop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Probably enjoyed a chance to play first base.
[SPEAKER_01]: Played the outfield.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did it every day, huh?
[SPEAKER_01]: Just thinking back the other day, Dizzy Dean died.
[SPEAKER_01]: We played an exhibition game in Moline, Illinois.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he was pitching against us.
[SPEAKER_01]: A fellow was pitching.
[SPEAKER_01]: A fellow was managing the ball club.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I was playing the outfield.
[SPEAKER_01]: We had John McKetty pitching, who used to be with the Giants at one time.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I had a home run off Dizzy Dean.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fella couldn't take that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He thought he was a good hitter, so he takes me out and puts himself in.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he and Dizzy Dean had a real gab fest.
[SPEAKER_01]: I could swing the stick pretty good for a pitcher if I wanted to.
[SPEAKER_01]: I soon found out.
[SPEAKER_01]: I wasn't up there very long when they told me, you're not getting paid for hitting, you're getting paid for pitching.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, did you, were you in service part of 46 too?
[SPEAKER_01]: I got out in the spring of 46.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was in exactly one year.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I came out I had an acute, acute prostatitis and that delayed me reporting for about two months.
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't join the club till about June 1st.
[SPEAKER_00]: You didn't pitch much that year?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I didn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just relieved.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just relieving probably pinch rent for somebody when they needed me.
[SPEAKER_01]: O'Neal was managing them.
[SPEAKER_01]: How'd you get along with Steve?
[SPEAKER_01]: I got along all right with him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Steve was a jolly Irishman.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: In 47 you had a 2-0 there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I was doing mostly relief work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Didn't get too much work because they had some other youngsters come along.
[SPEAKER_00]: By that time, I'm 35 years old.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, I was 32 then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Newhauser's great years in the war, you know, he won 29.
[SPEAKER_00]: Was he really that great a pitcher, or was it the war years?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Newhauser was probably the best left-hander that I had ever seen when he was in his heyday.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hal pitched great ball.
[SPEAKER_01]: He had a good curve, a good change, and a good fastball.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he could pitch.
[SPEAKER_01]: It didn't make any difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: War years won them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just happened that he did have his great years.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I would say that Newhouse could win any time.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't last too much after the war.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what makes you won one little game.
[SPEAKER_01]: I believe that his trouble probably could be pinpointed to the fact that he was pitching so much during the war years because of the lack of good pitches in their
[SPEAKER_01]: attempt to win the pennants.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, in 1944, for instance, he and Trout were the workhorses of the staff.
[SPEAKER_01]: One won, what, 28?
[SPEAKER_01]: The other one won 29 or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: 27, 29.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, they're way up there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by the time the end of the season rolled around, they were fagged out.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, they were worn out from the work so much.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the man just threw himself out in like four years.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's probably it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that hard work takes its toll.
[SPEAKER_01]: I found that out.
[SPEAKER_01]: My name probably isn't in the records as much as it could have been, but it doesn't mean I wasn't out there throwing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can remember one day, one stretch,
[SPEAKER_01]: where I got up 18 straight days to pitch, get ready to pitch and go in, and not get in the ballgame.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that takes something out of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, I've often wondered about that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, just watching the games on television, you see the...
[SPEAKER_02]: I think those poor men are going to be worn out before they ever get in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you see, those things happen, and that's something... Well, now you can see it, but in those days before television, you couldn't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it didn't impress you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now you see what's going on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wonder, well, there's a fellow warmed up last night, ready to get in the ballgame, and today he's in the ballgame.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, maybe he recovered enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: Chances are if that continues, about the second or third time he does that, he's going to lose his edge.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he might make that bad pitch when he wants to make a good pitch, and it ends up out of the park and the game's over.
[SPEAKER_00]: What was your best pitch?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I was strictly a sinker ball pitcher.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I threw a sinker ball overhanded.
[SPEAKER_00]: That curves and drops?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: A ball, it would come and go down, see?
[SPEAKER_01]: It would go straight down.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I'd come out of it this way.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I'd kick it with the thumb, see?
[SPEAKER_01]: Give it the spin to bring it straight.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that ball would just seem like it just dropped straight down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, most think a ball will throw and go like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Did you develop it pretty much yourself?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yes, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: How about a fastball?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, see, before I signed up to play pro ball, I pitched in high school.
[SPEAKER_01]: I pitched semi-pro.
[SPEAKER_01]: I played all over just to play.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was some background for making the pitch.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yes, surely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I hadn't had the background, I probably wouldn't have developed fast enough to get to the big leagues in two years.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, who was, did you have a toughest hitter to pitch against?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh my gosh, there were a load of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: The greatest one was that left-hander from Boston, Ted Williams.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was great.
[SPEAKER_01]: Terrific.
[SPEAKER_01]: How about DiMaggio?
[SPEAKER_01]: DiMaggio was the toughest.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was a tough right-handed hitter.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there were so many tough right-handed hitters, but Williams as a left-hander will stand out.
[SPEAKER_01]: in my mind, above all the left-handers and even right-handers for that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Overall, he was the best.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you go on down the line in those days, you had hitters like Fox, Paul hitters, DiMaggio.
[SPEAKER_01]: You had Joe Cronin playing short for Boston.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even in his twilight years, he was still a good hitter.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was a master at hitting, that Cronin was.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he's the one that taught Williams
[SPEAKER_01]: He and Harry Heilman, who was the broadcaster for Detroit, they've spent a lot of time with him, trying to impress upon him what he had to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hitting is an art.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can develop a hitter if he wants to, has the reflexes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just like pitching.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it easier to pitch to right-handers and left-handers?
[SPEAKER_01]: Some of them, you could say, are easier to pitch than others, but the plate's the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't move.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've got to get the ball over the plate to get somebody out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it really doesn't make any difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: How's your control?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I expect about first year it was pretty rough.
[SPEAKER_00]: You had more strikeouts than walks almost all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I guess you have to have 68, 57, 59, 55.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is one year here, you're 28, 29, 30, 40, 45, 36.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you're more strikeouts than most of the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, my control, you look at the records like that, and I'll say that it doesn't prove too much, because when you walk in from the bullpen and you've got men on base, you just can't throw the ball down the middle.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you're not warmed up properly, or if you're not sharp that day, you're going to walk.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what you're trying to do is keep that man from hitting that ball out of the park.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he's swinging for the fence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you don't try to give him anything too fat to hit at.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a lot of pressure on those relief pitches.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: You walk in there, and you've got one job to do, and that's get him out and make him hit your pitch.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you can't get it off the plate while you're in trouble.
[SPEAKER_01]: So.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, what happened after 47?
[SPEAKER_00]: Did you play more?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, at the end of season 47, I guess Billy Evans, who was general manager toward Barclay at the time, had made a deal with Seattle, whereas they got some ball player, I don't know who it was, and they had to send them somebody.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, they had all these young kids coming up, and they had to get rid of somebody, and I just happened to be one of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So they sold me out to Seattle in part of a deal.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I went out there and pitched that summer.
[SPEAKER_01]: How things go there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, a minor league is a minor league.
[SPEAKER_01]: I thought the Pacific Coast League was a real fast league.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when I got out there, they had some good ballplayers.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not taking anything away from them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But my goodness, we had ballplayers who couldn't stop a balloon.
[SPEAKER_01]: I swear, it was amazing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when you're used to having infielders and outfielders behind you,
[SPEAKER_01]: can go get a ball or a ground ball and walk out there and they drop them right in their hands.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think I won 13 games and lost 15.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I bet I lost half of those losses in the ninth inning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, there you lose two in a week up there because you pitch on Sunday and you'll pitch maybe Thursday or Friday again or Wednesday.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that where you had the week-long series?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: You went in on Tuesday and you played through Sunday.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you went out of that town, Monday was off, and you went into the next town and played six, seven, eight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you like that kind of arrangement?
[SPEAKER_00]: A little less moving around?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it doesn't make any difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: In those days, we played all-night baseball there except on the weekend.
[SPEAKER_01]: It didn't make any difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: You had more time for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You had more time to recoup.
[SPEAKER_00]: Did Mrs. Garcia go with you that year?
[SPEAKER_01]: She brought the boy out.
[SPEAKER_01]: My boy was born in 40 and they came out to Seattle that summer.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first time they'd come out wherever I'd been and spent the summer when school was out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So they, while I was on the road, they went sightseeing.
[SPEAKER_02]: They got an education.
[SPEAKER_01]: They had a real nice time, which I was happy because they couldn't do it before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Who was your manager in Seattle?
[SPEAKER_01]: Joe Joe White, the old outrigger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Was he a teammate with you before?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, he left before.
[SPEAKER_01]: I forget where Jojo went from Detroit.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think he went to St. Louis.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: He had a couple of real good minor leaguers after his major league career.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think he won some most valuable player award in the American Association maybe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, did you really enjoy playing ball?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I enjoyed it so much that I stayed in it as long as I was physically able.
[SPEAKER_00]: How long did you stay after?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I...
[SPEAKER_01]: After Seattle I was sold to Hollywood and that's where I hurt my arm in 49.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was trying to dick her for a contract and I was late reporting and I think I started just too soon and my whole arm just didn't have it, that's all.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I finished up in 49 and I tried it back in 50 with San Diego but it didn't come around so I just
[SPEAKER_01]: I called it a career and came home and went to work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, the bowling alley here, is this your own, when did this begin?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I worked in the drugstore until about 1960 and then we concocted the idea of putting up a bowling alley.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we had a little eight lane house down off on Neville Street and it's about the time the automatic pin setters were really in vogue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: I thought we could use a new establishment, so I got some people interested in what this building got.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've been working here ever since until July the 15th.
[SPEAKER_01]: And on July the 15th, we sold to this boy here and another boy about his age.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all I'm doing now is just finishing up my part of it, and I'm through.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am finished as of nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just going to loaf and fish.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, isn't that wonderful?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm 59 years old and I thought, well, I've got to give it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hello, Harry.
[SPEAKER_01]: Excuse me.
[SPEAKER_01]: He sees people.
[SPEAKER_01]: His wife bowled with me for years and he's quite a fisherman.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's retired.
[SPEAKER_01]: He goes down to North Carolina and down to Virginia and he's always kidding me about all the fish he catches.
[SPEAKER_01]: I call him Catfish Harry.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I won't be here.
[SPEAKER_00]: You mentioned fishing.
[SPEAKER_00]: In your off seasons, is that what you did a lot of?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I used to do a lot of fishing, and I used to do a lot of bowling while I was playing ball, and I did a lot of hunting.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when I opened this bowling alley, it tied me down so that I couldn't get out.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I opened it in 1960, and for 14 years, I've done nothing but work, from 9 o'clock in the morning to late at night.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had no time for anything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's reached the point now where
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I just don't have the steam I used to, that's all, and my legs won't carry me that many hours again, and I couldn't see my way clear when I could find some decent help, so I... Yeah, it's probably the best thing to do, though.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well... Now you can enjoy life, and you're young enough to enjoy it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's what my wife and I have decided.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you've got to call it quits sometime.
[SPEAKER_01]: The biggest decision I had to make was baseball.
[SPEAKER_01]: giving it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And heck, when you give up your first love and the only thing you've ever known how to do, then this is not hard for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I can... What did your father do?
[SPEAKER_01]: My father was a boilermaker for the Standard Oil Company in New Jersey, which is now Exxon.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he was... Did he play any ball?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, he was an immigrant from Poland.
[SPEAKER_01]: He came to New Jersey...
[SPEAKER_00]: I noticed your name was spelt G-O-R-S-Y.
[SPEAKER_01]: My original name, the spelled Polish name, is G-O-R-C-Z-Y-C-A.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for the convenience of the sportswriters, I tried to change it to G-O-R-S-C-Y-C-A, because I have an older brother who played ball in semi-pro, and that's what he used, and I just tried to use the same name.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when I came down here, instead of using the C, they injected an E.
[SPEAKER_01]: S-E-Y, instead of saying Gorsica, they would say Gorsica.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that didn't set too well with me, but after a while I got accustomed to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for the sportswriters' convenience, I just used G-O-R-S-I-C-A, just like you say it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gorsica.
[SPEAKER_00]: Did you have to go through some legal change?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your name is... No, I still keep my original name and social security number.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all that matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in business, like, I've used Gorsica.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Was your dad pretty proud of you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, he was.
[SPEAKER_01]: But like all fathers, a boy gets big enough in a family of 10 kids, why, he thought he ought to go to work.
[SPEAKER_01]: And playing ball wasn't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was too much fun.
[SPEAKER_00]: Did he see you pitch much?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: He saw me pitch in the World League Leagues.
[SPEAKER_01]: He used to come to New York when we played the Yankees.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I was fortunate enough to play in several games in the stadium.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, great.
[SPEAKER_01]: How about your mother?
[SPEAKER_00]: Was she living there?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, she was living then, yes, but she never did come out to the park.
[SPEAKER_01]: My dad was a baseball fan.
[SPEAKER_01]: He never missed a game, any chance he had.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wonderful of you to see me coming in so unannounced.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I'm glad I was here.
[SPEAKER_00]: By golly, you're lucky you caught me.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you happen to have any spare pictures around you could autograph them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's see, I might have some somewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: That'd be nice.